<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="biomart_processor">
    <title>Biomart query integration</title>

    <para>The Biomart system (<ulink
    url="http://www.biomart.org/">http://www.biomart.org/</ulink>) is a
    flexible data warehouse aimed at complex interlinked biological data sets.
    Originally developed for the Ensembl project it has now been generalized
    to allow other data providers access to its functionality. As an example
    the EBI's Biomart instance contains data from Ensembl, VEGA, DbSNP,
    UniProt and MSD data sets - Taverna's biomart query integration provides
    full search and retrieval functionality over these data sources. </para>

    <para>Biomart instances can contain multiple data sets, so the basic unit
    used in Taverna is the data set, or, more specifically, a single
    configured query over a single data set (although some dataset
    configurations allow links to a second dataset). </para>

    <section id="describing_biomart_service">
      <title>Describing a Biomart service</title>

      <para>A new Biomart service is added to the services panel from the
      right click menu on the top level node and selection of the ' Create new
      Biomart service... ' item. This then displays the following input dialog
      box : </para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/biomart_location.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The default location shown here is for the Biomart central server
      which contains seven distinct sets of datasets: Ensembl, SNP, VEGA,
      Uniprot, MSD, Wormbase and Dictybase. Once the user has specified the
      Biomart location a new node becomes available in the service selection
      panel, expanding this node shows the various distinct data sets
      available to query: </para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/biomart_scavenger.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section id="creating_biomart_query">
      <title>Creating a new Biomart query</title>

      <para>The query is created by dragging a dataset (shown in the panel
      above) into the advanced model explorer as with any other processor
      type. Similarly to the Beanshell scripting engine all Biomart processors
      require configuration before they are of any use within the workflow.
      The configuration section is accessible from the ' Configure biomart
      query... ' option in the right click context menu for the Biomart
      processor. When selected this will (after a brief pause while the
      configuration metadata is retrieved from the Biomart service) show the
      query configuration panel. The example below shows the initial
      configuration screen for the data source based on R. Norvegicus genomic
      data in Ensembl: </para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/create_biomart_query.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Biomart query processors have two sets of configuration, filters
      and attributes. Filters define restrictions on the query and are
      particularly important if the users wishes the query to return anything
      other than entire genome's worth of data. Attributes on the other hand
      define the values which the user is interested in. Conceptually filters
      are inputs (although not all filters appear as input ports) and
      attributes are outputs. </para>
    </section>

    <section id="conf_biomart_filters">
      <title>Configuring filters</title>

      <para>Filters are critical to almost all queries. If no filter is
      defined the query will return all records within the selected data set -
      as data sets generally correspond to entire genomes or databases these
      queries are therefore substantial. Filters are configured by selecting
      the ' Filters ' button at the top of the Biomart configuration panel:
      </para>

      <para>Filters are added by selecting the check box on the left. Filters
      may be grouped, so selecting the Band filters in the example below will
      add the Start and End filters to the Query. </para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/configure_biomart_filter.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The image above shows two distinct kinds of filters: The drop down
      lists represent filters over controlled vocabularies whereas the text
      entry boxes represent arbitrary textual inputs (although from the
      context here it is clear they are actually intended to be numeric
      values, at least for the chromosomal coordinate inputs). Some filter
      values change when other filters are configured - if the user selects a
      chromosome the band filters will be populated with appropriate values.
      </para>

      <para>The image below shows two more filter types, both based on boolean
      expressions. The pair of filters at the end of the page are simple
      boolean filters, they allow the user to specify whether a particular
      constraint must be satisfied, must not be satisfied or is ignored
      (filter not selected, the default). The filters at the top of the page
      are similar but the condition is configurable, the entire filter is
      constructed from a combination of the drop down subject with the
      predicate and object specified by the boolean selection: </para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/configure_biomart_filter2.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The image below shows an ID List based filter. These are used to
      constrain the query to only those results matching an explicitly stated
      list of values. The drop down list at the top of the filter selects the
      type of ID to filter on and the text entry area accepts IDs, one per
      line, to be used as values in the filter. Selecting the ' Browse '
      button allows the ID values to be read from a file - the file must have
      one ID per line. </para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/configure_biomart_filter3.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>The final kind of filter is one similar to the list based filter
      but where the item selected comes from a tree or taxonomy of terms:
      </para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/configure_biomart_filter4.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section id="biomart_param_filters">
      <title>Parameterised filters</title>

      <para>Some types of filters may manifest as inputs to the query
      processor. These are always optional - if no upstream processor is
      connected to the input the query will proceed exactly as configured. If,
      however, a data link is connected the data will override the value
      parameter for the query. For example, if the user wishes to construct a
      workflow where Ensembl Gene IDs are used to fetch the corresponding
      sequences he or she specifies a filter based on Ensembl Gene ID (as with
      the ID list filter above) and overrides the specified values by
      connecting a string list to the appropriate input. When the query is run
      by the enactor the ID list configuration will be modified by the input
      data. This applies to all filters other than the two boolean filter
      types, all except the ID list filter accept a single string as a value
      override. The example workflow ' BiomartAndEMBOSSAnalysis ' shows this
      facility in action: </para>

      <para></para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/biomart_workflow.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section id="biomart_dataset_filters">
      <title>Second dataset filters</title>

      <para>Some dataset configurations allow filters (but not attributes) to
      be selected for a second dataset. The second dataset section, at the end
      of the filters page, shows the datasets that can be selected: </para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/biomart_second_dataset.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>When a second dataset is selected the filters for that dataset are
      added to the end of the filters page, under the heading 'DATASET 2'. The
      ID used to link the two dataset can also be selected: </para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/biomart_link_dataset.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section id="conf_biomart_attributes">
      <title>Configuring attributes</title>

      <para>Attributes are configured by selecting the ' Attributes ' button
      at the top of the Biomart configuration panel. Attributes are themselves
      divided into pages. The required page is selected from the drop down
      list of available pages, in this case ' Features ', ' Structures ', '
      SNPs ', ' SNPsHomologs 'and ' Sequences '. Attributes can only be
      selected from one page. Any attributes selected from an attribute page
      will be removed from the query when another page is selected. </para>

      <section id="biomart_basic_attributes">
        <title>Basic attributes</title>

        <para>Selecting an attribute in one of the subpages states that the
        attribute should be returned for each record passing all defined
        filters. Each attribute therefore maps directly to an output on the
        processor - where possible sensible names are chosen for the processor
        outputs such that it is reasonably obvious which corresponds to which.
        The images below show the attribute selection page and the
        corresponding processor in the advanced model explorer : </para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo></screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/biomart_basic_attributes.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo></screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/biomart_ame.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>