<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="remote_execution">
  <title>Taverna Remote Execution</title>

  <para>The Taverna Remote Execution plugin is a plugin for Taverna that
  allows workflows to be run on a Remote Execution Server.</para>

  <para>To install the Remote Execution plugin use the Plugin Manager in the
  Tools Menu.</para>

  <para>Remote execution from Taverna depends upon the presence of Remote
  Execution Servers already installed on the web. A default Remote Execution
  Server is available in the Taverna Utilities subsection under downloads on
  the Taverna sourceforge site.</para>

  <section id="remote_execution_in_taverna">
    <title>Specifying Remote Execution Servers</title>

    <para>After installation of the Remote Execution plugin, a new perspective
    "Execute Remotely" is available. Within the perspective, the user can
    select from the set of Remote Execution Servers on which workflows may be
    run. When specifying a new Remote Execution Server, the user should enter
    the details given by the owner of the server.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/add_remote_execution_server.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The Remote Execution Server on which a workflow is to be run can be
    chosen from the selection menu. If a valid connection is made to the
    server, for example MyServer, then a message "Loaded jobs from MyServer"
    will appear in the log window at the bottom of the perspective. If a valid
    connection cannot be made then the message "Could not load jobs from
    MyServer" will appear.</para>

    <para>The chosen Remote Execution Server is periodically polled and the
    updated status messages will appear in the log window.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Running a workflow remotely</title>

    <para>To run a workflow remotely, edit or load the workflow design as
    normal. Switch to the "Execute Remotely" perspective. if necessary, choose
    a Remote Execution Server from the menu. Press the "Run workflow remotely"
    button. If any inputs are required for the workflow run then they can be
    entered as normal.</para>

    <para>Once a workflow has been sumitted to a Remote Execution Server, it
    is placed in a queue. The status of the queue is monitored every twenty
    seconds. When a submitted workflow reaches the front of the queue, when
    the Remote Execution Server has free resources, the workflow will enter a
    DEQUEUED state during which the server is initialized to run the workflow.
    Once the workflow has started running, its progress can be viewed by
    clicking on its entry in the list of jobs and clicking the View Progress
    button. Once the workflow has finished running, it will be marked as
    COMPLETE. The results can be viewed by clicking on the workflow's entry
    and then on the View Results button.</para>
  </section>
</section>