<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="logbook">
  <title>Taverna LogBook</title>

  <para>The Taverna Log Book (formerly known as the Taverna Provenance Plugin)
  is a plugin for Taverna that allows users to automatically log their
  experiments in a database and browse, reload, rerun and maintain past
  workflows.</para>

  <para>To enable the Log Book use the new Plugin Manager in the Tools
  menu:</para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/logbook_enable_plugin.png" scale=""
                   scalefit="" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>At the moment, in order to use the Log Book<emphasis role="bold">
  users require access to a MySQL database</emphasis>. (We are working on
  different implementations, both to improve scalability and, possibly, to
  avoid the need to access a database.) When you first switch to the Log Book
  perspective you will be prompted for the database details:</para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/logbook_mysql.png" scalefit="1" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>Note that you actually need two databases, one for data and one for
  metadata. The user interface allows you to reuse the same host, username and
  password across the two databases.</para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/logbook_databases.png" scalefit="1" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>It will also attempt to create the databases for you if they do not
  exist and if you have appropriate access rights.</para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/logbook_database_fail.png" scalefit="1" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>To activate the changes restart Taverna.</para>

  <para>After this, running a workflow in Taverna is automatically logged and
  can be browsed through the LogBook perspective (<ulink
  url="http://www.mygrid.org.uk/wiki/Mygrid/LogBook">http://www.mygrid.org.uk/wiki/Mygrid/LogBook</ulink>).
  Use the <emphasis role="bold">Refresh</emphasis> button to view the latest
  runs. (Note there is a delay between running and being able to browse the
  complete log.)</para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/logbook_clean.png" scalefit="1" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>The level of detail recorded is configurable via a Log Levels menu in
  the top left corner of the Settings tab. (Because of scalability issues, we
  recommend to use the <emphasis>Workflow inputs</emphasis> and
  <emphasis>outputs</emphasis> level of logging for most workflows, to avoid
  slowing down browsing.) For instance, this is the log of a run where only
  inputs and outputs are logged</para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/logbook_logged_results.png" scalefit="1" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>While here is the log of a run with full logging enabled.</para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/logbook_all_enabled.png" scalefit="1" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>And here is full logging for a workflow containing a nested
  workflow:</para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/logbook_nested_workflow.png" scalefit="1" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>The nested workflow run can be explored by right-clicking (ctrl-click
  on macs) on it.</para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/logbook_explore_nested_workflow.png"
                   scalefit="1" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>In general, right-clicking on the process runs pops-up a menu offering
  to add the process to the workflow or export the metadata to a file (as
  RDF). Selecting more than one process run allows to add all the selected
  processes to the workflow while maintaining the links.</para>

  <section id="logbook_wiki">
    <title>LogBook Wiki</title>

    <para>Further information about LogBook can be found within the LogBook
    Wiki page: <ulink
    url="http://www.mygrid.org.uk/wiki/Mygrid/LogBook">http://www.mygrid.org.uk/wiki/Mygrid/LogBook</ulink></para>
  </section>
</section>
