<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="running_taverna">
  <title>Running Taverna</title>

  <para>You should be able to run an installed Taverna system by invoking the
  'runme.bat' or 'runme.sh' files, the former being for Windows and the latter
  for Linux. If this fails to work you should re-check the installation, Java
  version and GraphViz version (linux only), and carefully read through the
  section on configuration. If you have done this and the system still doesn't
  work please let us know via the mailing lists.</para>

  <section id="enacting_a_workflow">
    <title>Enacting a predefined workflow</title>

    <para>As a first quick demonstration of Taverna you can load one of the
    example workflows. Select open workflow from the file menu. You should be
    presented with a file chooser dialog box, the exact appearance of which
    will be determined by your operating system. </para>

    <section id="loading_a_workflow">
      <title>Loading a workflow</title>

      <para>Workflow examples are stored in the 'examples' subdirectory of
      your Taverna installation, so use the file browser to navigate to this
      directory and select the 'ShowGeneOntologyContext.xml' workflow. This
      should result in the Advanced Model Explorer and Workflow Diagram panels
      being populated with the workflow defined in this file. There may be a
      short delay while Taverna contacts the network to get more information
      about the resources the workflow uses - if the delay is a very long one
      followed by an error you probably need to check the configuration of
      your proxy settings, see the configuration section for more
      details.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="enacting_current_workflow">
      <title>Enacting the current workflow</title>

      <para>Aside from creating and editing, the most useful thing to be able
      to do with a workflow is to run it. Select the 'Run Workflow' option
      from the file menu. If your workflow requires input, you will be
      presented with a new window - this is the place to enter the starting
      data on which the workflow is to run. In this case the workflow has a
      single input called 'termID'. Select ‘termID’ and right-click. You
      should see that the 'New Input' and 'New List' options are now available
      at the top of the window, click on the 'New Input' to create a single
      data input to the workflow. In this case, the workflow description has
      helpfully included an example of a sensible input value, the string
      'GO:0007601' (this term corresponds to 'vision' in the Gene Ontology -
      http://www.geneontology.org). In panel that has just appeared you should
      replace the 'Some input data goes here' with the input term, so try
      entering 'GO:0007601' as the description suggests (but without the quote
      marks). Once you have entered this input data you can press the 'Run
      Workflow' button at the bottom of this window to actually start the
      workflow engine off on the supplied input.</para>

      <para>The workflow run will be displayed in the ‘Results’ window. This
      window shows you the progress of the workflow and also the results on
      completion. Additionally, if anything goes wrong with the enactment you
      can interrogate other parts of this display to find out exactly what has
      happened (but we won't cover this here). You should see a table appear
      initially containing a list of the component operations along with their
      status, this will update until the workflow has finished and you can
      inspect the inputs and outputs of any given part of the workflow by
      selecting the process you're interested in and viewing the intermediate
      values from the bottom half of the window. Once the workflow completes
      you will jump into the results view.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="browsing_results">
      <title>Browsing results</title>

      <para>This particular workflow has a single output called 'graphical',
      which contains a single piece of data. Select the only available item in
      the list on the left hand side of the window and you should see a
      diagram of a sub graph of the Gene Ontology appear in the right hand
      panel - this is your workflow result (the diagram can be quite large,
      you might have to scroll around to see it). Congratulations, if this
      worked then you have installed and configured Taverna correctly and run
      your first workflow.</para>

      <para>If you were to want to save the workflow (there's not much point
      as we haven't changed anything) you would select the 'Save' option from
      the Advanced Model Explorer and save the document in the usual fashion
      for your operating system. You probably don't want to do this for now as
      there are no changes.</para>

      <para>To finish, and prepare for the next part of the introduction,
      you'll want to reset the workflow. Select the ‘Design’ view from the top
      of the workbench and then click on the red 'close workflow' icon in the
      ‘File’ menu. This just resets the definition, your results from the
      workflow invocation are still there; you can reset these by simply
      selecting ‘close’ in the top right corner of the ‘Results’
      window.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="very_simple_workflow">
    <title>Creating a (very) simple workflow</title>

    <para></para>

    <section id="workflow_inputs_and_outputs">
      <title>Workflow inputs and outputs</title>

      <para>First things first - the workflow needs to have an input, in this
      case the id of a sequence to fetch. You can create a new workflow input
      by right clicking on the 'Workflow inputs' node in the Advanced Model
      Explorer in the ‘Design’ view and selecting 'Create new input'. This
      will then ask you for a name for the input, you can change this later
      but for now use 'sequenceID'. Click on 'OK' and you should see your new
      input appear in the Advanced Model Explorer and Workflow Diagram
      windows.</para>

      <para>Similarly, the workflow will need an output. Follow an equivalent
      process but this time clicking on the 'Workflow outputs' node and using
      the name 'sequence' to create an output. Again, you should see the
      output appear in the two windows.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="single_sequence_fetch">
      <title>A single sequence fetch component</title>

      <para>Now that the workflow has an input and output it needs something
      to fit between to actually do the work. If you're familiar with the
      EMBOSS tool suite you might be aware that there's a program called
      'seqret' which can do exactly this, fetch a sequence from an ID.
      Fortunately the default services available from Taverna include a system
      called Soaplab at the EBI which contains all EMBOSS tools, including
      seqret. Go to the 'Available Services' window and either scroll down
      until you find it or, more sensibly, enter 'seqret' into the search box
      at the top and hit return. You should see the tree narrow to show you
      two matching operations (shown in yellow to denote soaplab services),
      'seqretsplit' and 'seqret'.</para>

      <para>To add the operation to the workflow you can drag the 'seqret'
      service from the 'Available Services' window into the 'Advanced Model
      Explorer' window, dropping the service into the empty space on the right
      of this window. You should hopefully see a new entry under the
      'Processors' node called 'seqret' with an array of other child items
      hanging off it - these are the available inputs and outputs to and from
      the newly created process.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="connecting_workflow_elements">
      <title>Connecting everything together</title>

      <para>You should see the workflow input, processor and workflow output
      in the 'Workflow Diagram' window, but they are not linked together yet.
      To link them, you need to right click on the 'sequenceID' input in the
      'Advanced Model Explorer' and select the 'seqret' child menu (under the
      'connect to…processor…seqret). This child menu will show you all the
      inputs in the seqret tool to which you can link your workflow input. The
      exact details of all these inputs will depend on the processor, in this
      case you want to link the sequenceID workflow input to the
      'sequence_usa' processor input. Select the 'sequence_usa' from the child
      menu and you should see the link appear in the workflow diagram.</para>

      <para>The remaining link in the workflow is from the output of the
      processor to the workflow output. Conceptually we always link from the
      source of the information to its destination (following the flow of
      data), so you'll need to expand the 'seqret' node in the Advanced Model
      Explorer (if it isn't already expanded) and scroll down to see the
      available outputs, denoted by purple circles with outgoing arrows. There
      are two outputs from this processor, 'report' and 'outseq', the one we
      want to use is the 'outseq'. Similarly to the first link, right click on
      the 'outseq' node and follow the 'Workflow outputs' child menu. There is
      only one workflow output so select it and you should observe the now
      completed workflow in the 'Workflow Diagram' window.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="describing_the_input">
      <title>Describing the input</title>

      <para>You can add descriptive information to the workflow inputs - this
      information is useful to guide potential users of your new workflow.
      Select the 'sequenceID' node by left clicking on it in the 'Advanced
      Model Explorer'. You should observe a tab at the top of the window with
      a purple icon and the text 'Metadata for 'sequenceID''. Select this tab
      by clicking on it.</para>

      <para>This is the metadata editor. For now we're only going to look at
      the free text description, the ontology and mime type tabs are too
      complex for this introduction. Select the 'Description' tab, enter some
      description of the input (i.e. a quick paragraph explaining that this
      input should hold the sequence ID to fetch and perhaps an example value
      - 'swallid:ops2_*' is a reasonable one), click the 'Update' button when
      you're done and jump back to the 'Workflow' tab to get back to the
      default view of the workflow.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="enacting_a_workflow2">
      <title>Enacting the workflow</title>

      <para>You should now be able to run the workflow just as in the previous
      section, try entering your example 'swallid:ops2_*' as the input
      (without the quotes) and you should see the status display (briefly)
      followed by the results which, all being well, should contain the
      fetched sequences in fasta format. If this worked then great, you've
      created a simple workflow from scratch and enacted it.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>