<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="release_notes_1.7.0.0_chapter">
  <title>Version 1.7.0 release notes</title>

  <toc></toc>

  <section id="t2_preview_overview">
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>Release notes for the 'Christmas' release of the Taverna Workbench,
    v1.7.0. This release contains the first technology preview of the new
    Taverna 2 (T2) codebase in the form of a plugin to translate a version 1.x
    workflow and run in the new enactor.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Fixes and new features in Taverna 1 codebase in this
    release</title>

    <para>See myGrid JIRA issue tracking for more detail at
    http://www.mygrid.org.uk/jira. The following outstanding issues with older
    releases have been fixed in this one :</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>TAV-557 : Starting Taverna without network fails with Null
        Pointer Exception</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>TAV-668 : BioMobyScavengerHelper should getFromModel</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>TAV-663 : Load system artifacts from plugin profile</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>TAV-647 : Open workflow request username/password</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>TAV-684 : Check new plugin repositories first</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>TAV-669 : XPath processor doesn't work with Java 1.6</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>This set of changes and fixes should make it easier for plugin
    authors depending on system level artifacts (such as the next Soaplab2
    processor). There are relatively few new features in the version one code
    because we've been focusing on...</para>
  </section>

  <section id="t2_tech_preview_1">
    <title>Taverna 2 Technology Preview 1</title>

    <para>The 1.7.0 release of the Taverna Workbench incorporates a technology
    preview of the new Taverna 2 (henceforth T2) enactment engine. This is not
    the full T2 release scheduled for June 2008, neither should it be regarded
    as suitable for production usage. In this release we have implemented the
    T2 functionality as a plug-in to the standard Taverna Workbench. This
    means that if you are not interested in the new enactor you can safely
    ignore it – the workbench will run exactly as normal and you can simply
    not use the extra perspective the new enactor plug-in will have created;
    the default ‘run workflow’ option will use the version 1.7 enactor.</para>

    <para>The version of the T2 enactor in this release has certain
    limitations; as the underlying model manipulated by the workbench is still
    the Taverna 1.x functionality such as staged iteration and configuration
    of the dispatch stack (used to define recursive behaviours, dynamic
    binding to abstract resources and similar) cannot be accessed (although
    they are implemented and usage of T2 from its API provides access to
    them).</para>

    <para>As the plug-in works on a ‘translate from T1 and run’ model we can
    only make use of features in T2 which are inherited from the T1 model –
    you could run a workflow with staged iteration, for example, but there’s
    no way to specify it in the UI at the moment. There are also limitations
    in terms of the available processor types. For each processor class (web
    service, biomart etc) in Taverna 1 we have to implement a translator and
    an equivalent activity class from the T2 API. Not all processor types are
    translated, specifically the API consumer and BioMoby types as well as any
    third party extensions of which we are unaware.</para>

    <para>The majority of the local worker types are translated, so workflows
    which make use of web services, local workers, beanshell scripts, biomart
    and soaplab should be translated without any issues. These limitations
    notwithstanding, the new enactor is capable of scaling far beyond the old
    version 1 series both in terms of memory usage and performance. The former
    is enabled by a pass-by-reference model, the latter through
    pipelining.</para>

    <para>In addition we have an enhanced monitoring facility which allows the
    state of nested workflow instances to be exposed and in this release we
    have implemented a naïve user interface to this functionality in the form
    of a monitor tree. There is also enhanced error checking, something that
    will extend throughout the new codebase and which allows us to catch
    potential problems in the workflow model before they occur, ideally before
    the workflow is run.</para>

    <para>In summary – the T2 functionality in this release of the workbench
    is intended to give you some insight into the potential capabilities of
    the full T2 release scheduled for June of next year. Bearing in mind the
    caveats above please do try to run your workflows in the new enactor and
    let us know how you get on – we are particularly concerned with workflows
    which fail where they worked or which return different results. There may
    be legitimate reasons for both these cases but we would like to know about
    them. We anticipate one more release where this T1 / T2 split exists
    sometime around the end of March next year before migrating across to the
    full T2 version in June. We should point out that the full T2 workbench
    will be capable of loading your current workflows, one of the purposes of
    this six month shakedown period is to ensure that this transition can take
    place with minimum disruption to your existing work – we understand and
    value the time you have spent creating it and have no intention of
    disregarding it.</para>

    <para>We're currently writing up documentation on the core architecture of
    Taverna 2 (as this is now sufficiently stable to be useful!), this will be
    made available online and notifications published to the mailing lists
    early next year.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="prototype_activity_palette">
    <title>Prototype Activity Palette</title>

    <para>This release also includes a prototype of the new activity palette
    (activity is the T2 version of processor, to a reasonable approximation),
    described in its own section in the user manual for this release. As with
    the new enactor the aim is to get feedback rather than be ready for
    mainstream production use.</para>

    <para>A guide to using the Activity Palette can be found at <ulink
    url="http://www.mygrid.org.uk/usermanual1.7/t2_guide.html#activity_palette">http://www.mygrid.org.uk/usermanual1.7/t2_guide.html#activity_palette</ulink>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>