<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="webservice_dataproxy">
  <title>Webservice Data Proxy</title>

  <section id="dataproxy_description">
    <title>Description</title>

    <para>The main purpose of the Data Proxy is to overcome the problem of
    webservices that return large items of data causing <ulink
    url="http://taverna.sourceforge.net/index.php">Taverna</ulink> to struggle
    or fail due to memory constraints. This is particularly the case when the
    service is invoked within an iteration. It solves this problem by allowing
    the user to select specific data elements for referencing, leading to the
    data to be stored on the proxy and the webserivce SOAP response is
    rewritten to replace the data itself with a URL to the actual data.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="dataproxy_installation">
    <title>Initial Configuration and Installation</title>

    <para>The Data Proxy source code can be downloaded from <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=74874">http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=74874</ulink>,
    or can be downloaded as a war file from from the same location. It is a
    JSP based application designed to be deployed in a JSP container such as
    <ulink url="http://tomcat.apache.org/download-55.cgi">Tomcat
    5</ulink></para>

    <para>Before deployment some minimal configuration is recommended. These
    are made by editing the web.xml which is found within the WEB-INF
    directory of the web-app (src/main/webapp if using the source bundle). The
    first change to make is to modify the location that the server
    configuration file is stored. This is configured by uncommented the
    block:</para>

    <screen>&lt;!-- Uncomment and modify the value to define the location that the configuration file
is stored. Without this parameter it is stored in the root of the webapp context.  
&lt;context-param&gt;
   &lt;param-name&gt;ConfigFileLocation&lt;/param-name&gt;
   &lt;param-value&gt;/tmp/config.xml&lt;/param-value&gt;
&lt;/context-param&gt;
--&gt;</screen>

    <para>and setting a suitable param-value for the ConfigFileLocation. If
    left commented out, the config.xml is stored in the root of web
    application context, but is not viewable.</para>

    <para>If your proxy is to be shared with other users, either internally or
    via the internet, then its advisable to block access to the configuration
    pages. This is done by uncommenting the block:</para>

    <screen>&lt;!-- Uncomment and modify if necessary to control access to the configuration pages
 You can define roles and users/passwords in the tomcat-users.xml of your tomcat installation. 
&lt;security-constraint&gt; 
  &lt;web-resource-collection&gt;
    &lt;web-resource-name&gt;Configuration&lt;/web-resource-name&gt;
    &lt;url-pattern&gt;/config/*&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
  &lt;/web-resource-collection&gt;
  &lt;auth-constraint&gt;
    &lt;role-name&gt;administrator&lt;/role-name&gt;
  &lt;/auth-constraint&gt;
&lt;/security-constraint&gt;

&lt;security-role&gt;
  &lt;role-name&gt;administrator&lt;/role-name&gt;
&lt;/security-role&gt;

&lt;login-config&gt;
   &lt;auth-method&gt;BASIC&lt;/auth-method&gt;
   &lt;realm-name&gt;WebService data proxy administration&lt;/realm-name&gt;
&lt;/login-config&gt;
--&gt;</screen>

    <para>You will also need to add a user, together with the role
    'administrator' (or another if you changed both role-name elements) to
    your tomcat-users.xml file, stored within your Tomcat installation within
    the config directory. An example is:</para>

    <screen>&lt;tomcat-users&gt;
  &lt;role rolename="administrator"/&gt;
  &lt;role rolename="manager"/&gt;
  &lt;user name="tomcat" password="tomcat" roles="tomcat,manager"/&gt;
  &lt;user name="elvis" password="12345" roles="administrator"/&gt;
&lt;/tomcat-users&gt;</screen>

    <para>By default BASIC authentication is used using the MemoryRealm. This
    is adequate for most cases, but bear in mind that names and passwords are
    not stored or transported as encrypted. The paranoid might want to
    investigate configuring different <ulink
    url="http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-5.0-doc/realm-howto.html">Realms</ulink>.
    The Realm is defined in META-INF/context.xml - note that with Tomcat 4
    this needs to be configured in the Tomcat conf/server.xml.</para>

    <para>The application is now ready to be deployed. If using the source
    code then it first needs to be build using <ulink
    url="http://maven.apache.org/">Maven2</ulink>, and running 'mvn package'
    which creates a war file within the target directory. It is deployed by
    either dropping the war file into the Tomcat installation webapp/
    directory, or via Tomcats <ulink
    url="http://tomcat.apache.org/tomcat-5.0-doc/manager-howto.html">Manager</ulink>
    utility.</para>

    <tip>
      <para>By default the context name is the same as the war file. If built
      from source you will probably want to remove the version number from the
      generated war file.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>Webservices are added and configured by visiting the address
    http://&lt;context&gt;/config, e.g
    http://localhost:8080/data-proxy/config. The first time this is visited
    some additional settings are requested:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Server Context - this should be the fully qualified context of
        the server. This needs to be set rather than relying on using the
        request since it is the base of the URL used to define access to the
        stored data, and proxied endpoints, wsdl and schemas. It should be set
        to the full address that the server is visible by, rather than the
        local address.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Data Storage Location - this is the root location that the data
        will be stored.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="dataproxy_webservices">
    <title>Adding Webservices</title>

    <para>Once configured you should be presented with a page that gives a
    table of defined webservices, and a form to add a new webservice.
    Webservices are added by specifying the WSDL address together with a
    meaningful name. Once successfully added it will appear in the table, any
    errors are reported within the page footer.</para>

    <para>The webservice appears in the table with its original WSDL address,
    and also a Proxy address. The Proxy address should be used when adding the
    service to Taverna, as this contains rewritten information to proxy any
    imported schemas and to point at the proxy endpoint. You can click on
    either link to view the WSDL.</para>

    <para>You can configure or delete the webservice by selecting it (by
    clicking the left hand table column) and selecting the appropriate icon
    from the toolbar.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="dataproxy_configuring">
    <title>Configuring Webservices</title>

    <para>Once on the configuration screen you are presented with a list of
    available operations and their response elements in a tree structure.
    These can be expanded to explore the operation response elements, which if
    complex can be expanded further to explore each inner element. The format
    for the element is &lt;name&gt;:&lt;type&gt;.</para>

    <para>Select an element and click the toggle button to turn referencing on
    or off. Once configuration is complete, click the save button to commit
    any changes.</para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo>Toggle elements for referencing.</screeninfo>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/dataproxy_toggle.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>The entire tree can be expanded or collapsed by clicking the '+' or
    '-' buttons respectively. Expanding the entire tree can be useful for
    finding elements previously selected to be referenced.</para>

    <note>
      <para>Bear in mind that selecting elements that are nested within
      another selected element will have no effect, since the data contained
      within the parent element is being redirected to a file so is never
      encountered for referencing.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="dataproxy_referencing">
    <title>Referencing in action.</title>

    <para>Once an operation response, or its nested element, has been selected
    for referencing the data contained within that element is no longer
    returned from the proxy, but instead is redirected to a file and replaced
    with a URL that provides access to the data stream. This means that a soap
    response that would normally return some data, would end up looking
    something like:</para>

    <screen>&lt;soapenv:Envelope xmlns:soapenv="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"&gt;
   &lt;soapenv:Body&gt;
      &lt;getDataChunkResponse xmlns="http://testing.org"&gt;
         &lt;getDataChunkReturn&gt;http://localhost:8080/data-proxy/data?id=8fa33c3f-c06e5b3a-getDataChunkReturn1&lt;/getDataChunkReturn&gt;
      &lt;/getDataChunkResponse&gt;
   &lt;/soapenv:Body&gt;
&lt;/soapenv:Envelope&gt;</screen>

    <para>So, the data itself has been replaced with a URL
    http://localhost:8080/data-proxy/data?id=8fa33c3f-c06e5b3a-getDataChunkReturn1.
    Opening this URL in a browser will either display the data (if text), or
    allow it to be downloaded (if binary). The identifier to the data is
    composed of 3 parts - the WSDLID, the Invocation ID, and the elementName
    The elementname is appended with an iteration count, which is important if
    the element is an item in a list. On the server itself this data is stored
    in the location &lt;Data Storage
    Location&gt;/&lt;wsdlID&gt;/&lt;invocationID&gt;/elementName1.</para>

    <para>This means that when adding the Proxy WSDL to Taverna as a WSDL
    Processor, the data produced as a processor output will contain the URL
    string rather than the data entity itself. This URL can be viewed in the
    results pane, or passed onto another processor. If passed on to another
    service being filtered by the proxy, then the data is <link
    linkend="dataproxy_dereferencing">de-referenced</link> back to the original data
    before reaching the 'real' service endpoint.</para>

    <note>
      <para>If the data selected for referencing is part of a complex type
      where there are further child elements, the XML structure gets written
      to the file unwrapped, and is presented through the URL, just as it
      occurs within the SOAP message.</para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="dataproxy_dereferencing">
    <title>Data dereferencing</title>

    <para>If in the outgoing soap request a URL matching the data streaming
    servlet (&lt;Server Context&gt;/data?id=) is encountered within the
    content of a data element it is dereferenced back to the original data.
    This is useful so that a Taverna workflow can orchestrate a large data
    entity being passed between 2 (or more) service operations without ever
    actually passing through Taverna itself.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="dataproxy_housekeeping">
    <title>Data housekeeping</title>

    <para>No code in any of the Data Proxy will EVER delete any data. To
    remove old unwanted data you need to physically delete the files within
    the Data Storage Location specified during configuration.</para>

    <para>Data can be moved to a new location, and the Data Storage Location
    modified, as long as it keeps the original directory structure. The data
    streaming servlet, and the de-referencing of the data, relies on the
    components of the identifier in the URL being translated to and from this
    directory structure. This structure is described in the section on <link
    linkend="dataproxy_referencing">referencing.</link></para>
  </section>

  <section id="dataproxy_constraints">
    <title>Current constraints and future work.</title>

    <para>Being an early release there are currently a few contraints:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>The schema is not rewritten to reflect changes in the data
          structure. If a complex type is set to be referenced then the schema
          will not reflect that this has changed to a anyURI or xsd:string
          element. A current workaround for this is to make a copy of the
          original WSDL to a file, hand craft the schema by hand but leaving
          the rest of the WSDL intact, and point the Data Proxy at this copy
          of the WSDL.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>If a service defined as RPC/encoded and the response consists
          of a complex type, then the response may use <ulink
          url="http://www.w3.org/TR/2000/NOTE-SOAP-20000508/#_Toc478383512">SOAP
          Encoding</ulink> leading to the XML structure being
          multi-referenced. The data proxy does handle this. This problem does
          not affect document/literal style services or rpc/encoded services
          that return a primitive type.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist> These will be addressed depending upon the uptake of
    this utility and the impact of these constaints.</para>
  </section>
</section>