<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="available_services">
  <title>Available services</title>

  <para>This component provides facilities to manage the various services
  available to the workflow designer and allows the user to manage service
  libraries, create instances of a service in the form of a processor within
  the workflow, search services and other such functionality.</para>

  <section id="service_panel_organisation">
    <title>Service panel organisation</title>

    <para>Services are shown in a hierarchical view. The exact semantics of
    this hierarchy vary by service type; soaplab, for example, has some
    concept of service categories so the view for a soaplab server shows the
    top level installation, then child nodes corresponding to the various
    categories and finally leaf nodes corresponding to actual services:</para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo></screeninfo>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/soaplab_available_services.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>Biomoby services are located by accessing a central moby repository.
    In this case the hierarchy is constructed from a root node specifying the
    repository, then child nodes for each site hosting services and leaf nodes
    for each individual service:</para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo></screeninfo>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/biomoby_available_services.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    <para>In general all service types follow this pattern, the leaf nodes are
    always individual services with other nodes representing some kind of
    containment.</para>

    <para>A special case is that of workflow nodes - these are nodes
    representing entire Taverna workflows but in addition may be expanded to
    show copies of the services within those workflows, effectively allowing
    the user to reuse components from another workflow without having to
    figure out where the component was originally found. An example of this is
    shown below:</para>

    <screenshot>
      <screeninfo></screeninfo>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/workflow_available_services.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
  </section>

  <section id="services_adding_to_workflow">
    <title>Adding instances of a service to the workflow</title>

    <para>The primary function of the service panel is to allow users to
    create new processors within the current workflow. This can be
    accomplished either through drag and drop or through the context menus
    available by right clicking on the nodes in the service panel.</para>

    <section id="services_drag_and_drop">
      <title>Creation using drag and drop</title>

      <para>Any node representing a service may be dragged from the service
      selection panel into the AME. This also applies to nodes representing
      entire workflows in which case the workflow will be created as a nested
      workflow processor. The effect of a drop into the AME varies by
      location. If the node is dropped into area 1 in the diagram below it
      will be created as a new processor. If, however, area 2 is the target
      the effect will be to create a new alternate to the processor node the
      service was dragged onto.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/add_processor_dad.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section id="services_menu_options">
      <title>Creation using menu options</title>

      <para>As an alternative, new processors may be created by right clicking
      on the service to be used; this shows the following options:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/add_processor_menu.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

      <para>Selecting <emphasis role="bold">'Add to model'</emphasis> will
      create a new processor with the same name as the service node. If this
      name is unavailable the workbench will append a number to it until it
      is, creating processor names such as '<emphasis
      role="bold">getDot1</emphasis>' rather than '<emphasis
      role="bold">getDot</emphasis>'. If the '<emphasis role="bold">Add to
      model with name...</emphasis>' is selected a dialogue is shown allowing
      the user to explicitly name the processor (processors may be renamed at
      any time from the AME by double clicking on their names there). The
      '<emphasis role="bold">Add as alternate to...</emphasis>' submenu allows
      the user to specify that the new processor should be created as an
      alternate to the selected pre-existing processor in the workflow.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="services_discovering_for_processor">
      <title>Discovering the service for a given processor</title>

      <para>As processor names often do not correspond to the names of items
      in the service panel it can be helpful, especially when debugging a non
      functional workflow, to find out which node in the service panel would
      have produced a specific processor in the AME. To do this simply drag
      the processor node from the AME into the tree area of the service panel,
      the node corresponding to the service of which the processor is an
      instance will be selected and displayed in red if found. Some nodes,
      most noticeably beanshell scripts and string constants, may not be found
      correctly, this is due to the way they are represented within the
      services panel but for the majority of cases this approach works.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="services_importing_workflow">
      <title>Importing a workflow from the service panel</title>

      <para>An additional option appears in the context menu when right-clicking on a workflow
      node. This '<emphasis role="bold">Import
      workflow...</emphasis>' option allows the user to import the entire
      contents of the workflow specified in the same way as if it had been
      loaded from the AME. Rather than being created as a nested workflow
      processor the workflow is loaded alongside any existing processors. To
      avoid name collisions (all processor names must be unique within a given
      workflow) the user can in addition specify a prefix string which is
      prepended to all processor names in the new workflow. The dialogue to
      set the prefix is shown when the '<emphasis role="bold">Import
      workflow...</emphasis>' option is selected. Pressing return without
      entering any text will be interpreted as 'no prefix'.</para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/import_workflow_from_sp.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section id="services_searching">
      <title>Searching over the service panel</title>

      <para>The service panel may be searched by regular expression. For
      convenience the text box in the toolbar allows the user to enter a
      fragment of a service name and use either the return key or the search
      icon to the right of the text box. As the user types all matching
      services are shown highlighted in red, when the search is activated by
      return key or search button the tree is collapsed then re-expanded to
      show all nodes matching the specified search. This is particularly
      useful if the user knows exactly what he or she is looking for. The
      image below shows the search in action:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/search_service_panel.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section id="services_descriptions">
      <title>Fetching service descriptions</title>

      <para>Some types of service support a level of self description.
      Services based on soaplab, Biomoby and Nested Workflows can
      all provide textual descriptions of the operation the service performs.
      In order to fetch these descriptions the user can select the '<emphasis
      role="bold">Fetch descriptions</emphasis>' option from the context menu
      on any node in the service panel other than the root. This will then
      start fetching descriptions in the background and adding them to the
      service panel as and when they are found. Descriptions are fetched for
      all nodes below the selected one in the tree, including the selected
      node itself. So, the user can fetch descriptions for a single operation,
      soaplab category, entire biomoby installation etc:</para>

      <screenshot>
        <screeninfo></screeninfo>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/fetch_service_descriptions.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </section>

    <section id="services_populating">
      <title>Populating the services panel</title>

      <para>The service panel may be populated with available services in
      several distinct ways:</para>

      <section id="context_menu">
        <title>Context menu</title>

        <para>The context menu for the root node in the service panel labelled
        'Available Processors' can be used to add single 'scavengers' to the
        tree. A scavenger in this context is a part of Taverna's code which
        allows it to find services. There are a variety of options the user
        can select:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo></screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/context_menu.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The Talisman scavenger can be ignored here. It is extremely
        specialized and only applicable to those already using the Talisman
        web application system. The others, however, operate as
        follows:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">BioMoby scavenger</emphasis> This
            scavenger asks the user for the location of a Moby Central
            repository. It uses this repository to determine all available
            hosts and their services and adds the tree thus created to the
            service panel.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">API consumer </emphasis>This allows
            the import of pre-prepared Java APIs. This is used in conjunction
            with Java libraries augmented with annotations created by the API
            Consumer tool (see that tool's documentation for more
            information). This allows the import of existing component systems
            such as caBIG, BioJava, JUMBO, CDK etc.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">WSDL scavenger</emphasis> This
            scavenger asks the user for the location of a Web Service
            Description Language (WSDL) file on the web. It inspects this file
            to pull out all appropriate operations and adds them as WSDL based
            service nodes to the services panel.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Styx Grid scavenger</emphasis> This
            service type is currently experimental and interfaces to the peer
            to peer streaming enabled service framework developed using the
            Styx protocols either natively or layered on top of the Inferno
            embedded operating system. If selected this asks for the host and
            port on which the SGS container is running and presents each
            contained service under a node representing the host in the
            services panel.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">BioMart instance</emphasis> Asks the
            user for the parameters required to connect to a BioMart data
            warehouse. Uses the metadata available from the warehouse to get
            all available data sets and adds each set to the services panel
            under a new Biomart node.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">BioMart registry</emphasis> New from
            version 1.2 onwards, this allows the user to specify the location
            online of a Biomart registry xml file. By default Taverna will
            load the public Ensembl+MSD+Vega+DbSNP registry hosted at the EBI
            and Sanger Institute in the UK. </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Workflow scavenger</emphasis> This
            allows workflows to be added as services and asks the user for the
            URL to a single XScufl definition file. It adds the workflow as a
            node in its own right and also adds each processor within the
            workflow as a child node before adding the workflow node to the
            services panel.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Soaplab scavenger</emphasis> This
            scavenger asks the user for the root URL of a soaplab server. It
            interrogates the server to get all available application
            categories then for each category creates a list of services in
            that category. </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Collect from web</emphasis> Asks the
            user for an initial URL, uses this to start a web crawl looking
            for XScufl definitions and WSDL files. If it finds any it will add
            them below a top level 'web crawl starting from...' node in the
            service panel. This scavenger runs in the background as it can
            potentially take a considerable amount of time to complete.
            </para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Collect from model</emphasis> This
            option enables the inspection of the current workflow (shown in
            the AME) and infers the existence of any services the workflow
            uses. For example, if a workflow uses one operation from a soaplab
            installation this operation will notice that and add a new soaplab
            scavenger which will then contain all the other operations that
            the server supports. This is an explicit version of the implicit
            functionality enabled by the 'watch loads' checkbox. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section id="services_watch_loads">
        <title>'Watch Loads' option</title>

        <para>If the '<emphasis role="bold">Watch loads</emphasis>' checkbox
        in the Available Services toolbar is selected the current workflow
        will be watched. Any time a new service is added the services panel
        will initiate a new '<emphasis role="bold">Collect from
        Model</emphasis>' operation. This means that a user can import all the
        services a particular workflow uses by simply loading the workflow
        then resetting it.</para>
      </section>

      <section id="services_direct_invocation">
        <title>Direct service invocation</title>

        <para>Although most services are only useful when composed into
        workflows there may be occasions where it is handy to invoke a single
        service directly. Specific cases are where the service is providing
        some controlled vocabulary such as a list of valid database names, or
        where the node is actually a complete workflow as in the diagram under
        the 'Drag and Drop' section below. Any service node within the tree
        may be called directly by right clicking on it and selecting
        '<emphasis role="bold">invoke</emphasis>' from the context
        menu:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo></screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/direct_service_invocation.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>

        <para>The behaviour differs slightly depending on whether the node
        selected is a single service (as in the example above) or an entire
        workflow. If a service is selected this service will be inserted into
        a trivial workflow containing workflow inputs and outputs
        corresponding to the service inputs and outputs. In the case of a
        workflow the workflow is run directly. In either case the enactment
        engine is used to run the new workflow so the various input
        specification behaviours are the same as those used when running the
        main workflow from the workbench. </para>
      </section>

      <section id="services_drag_and_drop2">
        <title>Drag and drop</title>

        <para>XScufl definitions or directories may be dragged onto the
        <emphasis role="bold">toolbar</emphasis> area of the Available
        Services window. This initiates a file traversal looking for XScufl
        files, and can be used to load a library of workflows from the local
        file system. In a sense this is the file equivalent of the 'Collect
        from Web' option in the context menu. If a directory is dropped a
        corresponding hierarchy in the tree is created, all leaf nodes are
        workflows and their child processes:</para>

        <screenshot>
          <screeninfo></screeninfo>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/dnd_to_service_toolbar.png" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </section>

      <section id="services_initial_services">
        <title>Default initial services</title>

        <para>The service panel can be preloaded with services by specifying
        various defaults in the mygrid.properties file (see the <link
        linkend="default_services">default services</link> section). Specifically,
        the following service types can be preloaded into the service
        panel:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Web services based on a WSDL description</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Soaplab installations</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Biomoby Central Directories</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Web crawl based searches for workflows and WSDL files</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

        <para>The values for these properties correspond to the user inputs
        required for the equivalent context menu options.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
