<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="interaction_service">
  <title>Taverna Interaction Service</title>

  <para>The majority of components within a workflow are computer based, data
  sources, analysis algorithms and the like. In many analyses, however, there
  is a requirement to interact with people as part of the analysis process.
  This raises an issue - how can we define a human interaction within a
  workflow? The solution adopted here is the Interaction Service, an
  extensible mediation layer inbetween the automated workflow system and a
  user or users.</para>

  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata align="left" fileref="images/interactionlogo.png" />
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <section id="interaction_service_in_taverna">
    <title>Using the Interaction Service from Taverna</title>

    <para>Once you have an interaction service (or access to someone else's)
    you can add it to the Taverna services panel like any other resource. This
    will expose all available <emphasis role="bold">interaction
    patterns</emphasis> as processors to add to the workflow. The interaction
    pattern defines the input data for the interaction, the method by which
    the interaction takes place and the result data. We have two default
    patterns available, a simple 'accept or reject' pattern and a more complex
    one based on a modified form of the Artemis sequence editor.</para>

    <para>The patterns will, when invoked, send an email to the target user.
    This email consists of various HTTP links which the user selects to either
    reject the interaction or proceed. In the case of the trivial 'accept /
    reject' pattern the data to be reviewed is sent in the email (so text
    only) and links below the data allow the user to accept or reject the
    data, the decision is sent back to the workflow engine and appears as the
    output of the interaction processor. The sequence review processor is
    significantly more complex; the link causes a modified version of Artemis
    to load on the user's desktop - the modification allows us to populate the
    sequence editor pane with the input data from the interaction processor.
    The user edits the annotation as per usual and commits it back along with
    a textual comment describing the changes and, as before, the workflow
    continues.</para>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/interaction_example.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </section>
</section>