<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="custom_perspectives">
  <title>Custom perspectives</title>

  <para>Taverna now incorporates what we call ‘perspectives’ for particular
  tasks. The default perspectives are Design and Results for creating
  workflows, and examining the results respectively. Plugins that include User
  Interface components will also define their own perspectives.</para>

  <para>These perspectives will be adequate for the majority of users, but the
  adventurous user may decide to create a perspective of their own. Custom
  perspectives are created by selecting “New” under the “Edit perspectives”
  menu which is under the “Advanced” menu. </para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/new_perspective_menu.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>After providing a name for the perspective, this will then generate a
  blank perspective. In order to edit this perspective you need to enter Edit
  mode which is achieved by selecting Edit from the same menu. Note that only
  custom perspectives may be edited and it is not possible to switch
  perspectives whilst editing. Once in Edit mode, 3 icons appear in the top
  right hand corner – one to create a split pane - <inlinegraphic
  fileref="images/icon_create_pane.png" /> , another to create a tabbed pane -
  <inlinegraphic fileref="images/icon_create_tabbed_pane.png" /> , and a third
  to add a component - <inlinegraphic
  fileref="images/icon_add_component.png" /> .</para>

  <para>When creating a split pane, additional options appear to toggle
  between a vertical and horizontal split - <inlinegraphic
  fileref="images/icon_vertical_pane.png" /> and <inlinegraphic
  fileref="images/icon_horizontal_pane.png" /> , and also to delete the split
  pane - <inlinegraphic fileref="images/icon_delete_pane.png" /> . The size of
  each split pane can be adjusted by dragging the dividing bar.</para>

  <para>When creating a tabbed pane options appear to add a tab -
  <inlinegraphic fileref="images/icon_add_tab.png" /> , or delete a tab -
  <inlinegraphic fileref="images/icon_delete_pane.png" /> . The tab may also
  be assigned a colour, and if there are multiple tabs the order can be
  modified. Also at the top left of the pane is a text field allowing the tab
  to be assigned a name.</para>

  <para>The perspective comes to life once you start adding to components to
  it. This is achieved by selecting add component <inlinegraphic
  fileref="images/icon_add_component.png" /> . There are two ways to add a
  component. </para>

  <para>One way is to add a named component using <inlinegraphic
  fileref="images/icon_add_named_component.png" /> - Named components are
  components that have been previously named in other perspectives and adds
  the same instance of the component. This is useful if you want a component
  to remain initialised between perspectives, e.g. to keep the Service panel
  populated. </para>

  <para>New instances of a component, and components that haven’t been named
  can be added by selecting an SPI with <inlinegraphic
  fileref="images/icon_spi.png" /> . SPI means Service Provider Interface, and
  is a technical way of describing a plugin extension point. Once this is
  selected you will need to select the interface – this is by default
  UIComponentFactorySPI and this will almost always be what you wish to
  select. If you don’t know what this means you won’t need to change it, so
  don’t worry. Once this has been selected an icon appears providing a list of
  suitable components.</para>

  <screenshot>
    <screeninfo></screeninfo>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/add_component_to_perspective.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>

  <para>Once the component has been added it can be named using <inlinegraphic
  fileref="images/icon_name_component.png" /> .</para>

  <para>Once the new perspective has been created toggle out of Edit mode by
  select “Stop editing” from the “Edit Perspectives” menu to be able to switch
  between perspectives again. The perspective will remain until it has been
  deleted, even between Taverna restarts, but if you are particularly proud of
  your new perspective you may wish to save it.</para>
</section>