<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Using the T2 Plugin</title>

  <section>
    <title>Using the Plugin</title>

    <para>The plugin contains 3 main panels: a view of the currently opened
    workflow, the process being executed and the results. There are also 4
    buttons: Test, Run, Reset &amp; Preferences.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/t2_plugin_workflow.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>Test allows you to perform a workflow healthcheck. This will check
    that the workflow can be translated from the old style scufl model to the
    T2 style and that any web-service endpoints are responding. The top screenshot 
    is from a failed check while the bottom one is a success</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/t2_healthcheck_fail.png" />
        </imageobject>
   
        
      </inlinemediaobject>
      </para>
      <para>
      <inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/t2_healthcheck_pass.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>Preferences allows you to select a location for the data manager to
    store the entities, this is also remembered between plugin
    sessions.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/t2_plugin_preference.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>Run pops up a panel which allows you to enter the inputs for the
    workflow. Clicking on run will execute the workflow with your inputs and
    then present them in the bottom right panel. The data manager will have
    registered any inputs and any results and the serialised versions can be
    browsed on disk.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/t2_plugin_create_entity.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>The sample input data below shows a list containing a Data Document
    (with a File Reference Scheme &amp; a Http Reference Scheme), a Literal
    Blob (&gt;80 characters) and an Integer Literal.</para>

    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/t2_plugin_create_entity2.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>

    <para>Clicking on run workflow executes the workflow and generates the
    results. During the run the workflow status is monitored and shown to you.  In the example results below a beanshell was concatenating “xxx”
    to a string input of “Hello Taverna Users”.</para>
    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/t2_plugin_monitor.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>
    <para><inlinemediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/t2_plugin_workflow_complete.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </inlinemediaobject></para>
  </section>
</chapter>